[SPEAKER_03]: So, most people who practice the dhamma today, will do so as householders and not as monastics.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what people may not necessarily realize, is that to be a householder today, is probably quite different than being a householder back in the Buddha's day.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I thought we could explore some of the unquestioned views and assumptions and blind spots, because people might think that they are in the same position to approach and practice dhamma as householders back in the day, but actually, there might be a lot of additional dust
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I thought we could go into it and see what's involved.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what would be
[SPEAKER_03]: One of the main differences that would stand out, in terms of how people generally live their lives now, compared to back in India, when the Buddha was alive.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, certainly, the level of comfort these days, we live a little bit like kings and queens.
[SPEAKER_02]: The degree of safety, security, much higher in terms of comfort, how we live.
[SPEAKER_02]: I would say that, you know, with all the health care, for example, or food,
[SPEAKER_02]: You can rely on the food which is available.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's more kind of predictable, more kind of secure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Less exposure to the kind of uncertainty and the changes which involve in the natural process of life.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so some developments, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Better hygiene standards, health care, things like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's definitely progress.
[SPEAKER_03]: And there is a widespread idea, actually, we should question this idea of progress.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's a fatal mistake to conflate the outer technological level where there has been progress down the ages.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if people
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't put that on the right level and think that because they have been born in the 20th or 21st century that they are therefore necessarily better humans than back in the day.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: When you take the progress on the inner existential level, then that's already a sort of a conceited, arrogant take on things that will become an obstacle if you actually want to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, there is that progress.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that progress outwardly, technologically, is not actually a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, you also mentioned the level of comfort.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that might actually be an obstacle in the context of practicing dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: In fact, there's even this one sutra where the Buddha is praising the Licchavis for using wooden blocks as pillows.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then he said the same thing about monks.
[SPEAKER_03]: Saying when monks indulge in comfort, you know, having comfortable pillows made out of down and things like this, then the Māra, the evil one, will gain access to them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, we should make a distinction between the desire for comfort
[SPEAKER_03]: And, just technological innovations taking place, because that can't be stopped, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: We're not saying go back to the Middle Ages.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's no difficulty with that outer progress, but it seems to me that the desire for comfort and the safety that you mentioned,
[SPEAKER_03]: The... in essence, that means, basically, that people don't really want to feel feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what kompa is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It allows them to not feel.
[SPEAKER_03]: It allows you to not feel feeling which is present.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, as we have discussed in quite a few talks already, the whole practice of dhamma
[SPEAKER_03]: It takes place on the level of craving, which is always in relation to feeling, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh... craving to continue pleasant feeling or craving against unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: But how can one discern and practice the Middle Way, which takes place on that level, if one is living nowadays a life that is dominated by the wish for comfort, that that allows you to basically hardly feel anything?
[SPEAKER_03]: That is going to be a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not the fact that healthcare might be accessible or that you can get in the car rather than walk somewhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, but you see, this is hardly being talked about.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people might think, oh, I'm a householder now.
[SPEAKER_03]: I read discourses and I see that householders become noble disciples.
[SPEAKER_03]: Therefore, I'm going to read the discourses and I can also become a noble disciple.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that is way... And continue living the same way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and continue living the same way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that seems to me a blind spot that people are probably not sufficiently aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this was kind of... well, this is something you say often, so, kind of ripping it from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, the concept of
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, these days, I notice, like, if I get sick, say I, like, wake up in the middle of the night with, like, a splitting headache, my immediate thought is, like, I can, I can just see myself, like, taking safety and, like, oh, you know, I can just go to the hospital, they'll fix it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's kind of that implicit assumption that any problem can be solved.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a 30-minute drive to the nearest hospital, that was absolutely not a thing in ancient India.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those householders, you... yeah, something significantly less scary than waking up with a headache.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the slightest thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get a cut and it's infected.
[SPEAKER_01]: That could be... that could be... antibiotics.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the danger was much more apparent.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so that's one thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you see, it's a good thing that people might now live longer lives.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't think anyone here is against it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if it comes down, if it comes with the complacency of all those things that we just mentioned, yeah, that is then going to become an issue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then you actually need to make double efforts in order to touch upon the basic uncertainty that comes with having been born in the first place.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, you're covering up the fact that
[SPEAKER_04]: Feelings arise out of your control.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you have ample means to deal with feelings when they arise, you will not be forced to find out that actually the reason why those feelings make you suffer is craving, not the feelings.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there's that level as well, but it's not a coincidence also that
[SPEAKER_04]: The practice of dhamma, in itself, also becomes a way of trying to find comfort.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not just the external comfort that's taken for granted, as we said, but internally, I also want to not even feel things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Aha, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, most practice will be geared towards that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, well, that's what we discussed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like an internal spa or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas, actually, it is about uncovering the liability to old age, sickness, death.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that no scientist has been able to prevent.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they probably will not be able to do that either.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, one is still subjected to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you see, then people can very easily think like, yeah, well, that's in the future for one thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sickness and death.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm now young, I'm still healthy, so I postpone that into the future.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even if that's going to happen, well, let's just hope that I have a comfortable death.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe a shot of morphine if it becomes too painful, and then I die, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't suggest we now go into the whole discussion of rebirth, but there is that nihilism sitting there in the background.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you assume this is the only life, you basically want to sit out the ride as comfortable as possible, without then realizing that, against those assumptions, the dhamma goes 180 degrees the other way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh... the...
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so you want to basically be... if you want to understand impermanence, which could also say the form of uncertainty, then you need to stop covering it up, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, because you can... you can... Actually, that's one slightly ironic thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, impermanence would be along those lines of
[SPEAKER_04]: Your body being liable to sickness, you being liable to die at any time, the things that you're attached to being liable to be taken away at any time, that's what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_04]: But because we are so used to not thinking about those things anymore, like our existence is basically founded upon ignoring those things so that we can be at ease,
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, when people try to think about impermanence, it totally doesn't affect, at all, that level where that comfort is.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just externally, you know, these sense objects are constantly changing, and my sights are popping in and out of existence every second.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, eh... that that uncertainty of your being, where your your actual attachments are established, that that's completely taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's all, eh...
[SPEAKER_04]: It all goes hand-in-hand, almost, like, you know, the way you externally live your life, and then not taking that, not questioning that, and then approaching the dhamma with the same attitude.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like... Keeping it at a distance.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, everything, like, at arm's length.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not enough now to have all these external comforts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, I want to have comfort of the wrong kind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, obviously, you could say liberation is a sort of comfort, but no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like the wrong kind of comfort, in the sense of freeing myself from feelings,
[SPEAKER_04]: Instead of freeing myself from craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, now people want to have even that, even on the level of their mind, not just on the external level.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, like I said, it's just a continuation of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: And also another aspect that might not be necessarily thought about in terms of
[SPEAKER_04]: There's a big difference in how those people were living.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's a big difference in
[SPEAKER_04]: For example, if you read the discourses and you see what situation those people were in, the ones who were householders, like Kannada Pindika, Risaka, these famous lay disciples that people would sometimes quote as proof that you can be, you know, living a household life and having children and still practicing the dhamma, the part that they would forget is that these people already had children, were already married,
[SPEAKER_04]: When they encountered the dhamma, it's not that they, at 17 years old, became sotāpanas, and then they chose to go the route of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's a very different situation, because if you already have children, well, they wouldn't just...
[SPEAKER_04]: Factually, back in those days, if the man of the family abandons the wife and the children, there's a very high likelihood that they won't be able to make it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it was a very different thing for somebody to...
[SPEAKER_04]: It was a very dangerous thing for somebody to choose to ordain, no matter how much they wanted, like, ideally, to do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Back in those days, than it is today, because today we have, like, health care, you know, social security.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, I'm not saying you should abandon your children nowadays just because of that, but the point is, like, clearly, there is a very different situation in that sense, and they would have been staying with their family with a very different reason, or with a very different context.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, somebody might be doing it... doing today.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're saying even the kind of... well, one of the requirements for ordaining as a bhikkhu is you need your parents' permission.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, in that time, like, you had children to watch after you when you were old.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that was your kind of survival token.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's what you had to do to survive is have kids.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, I'm not asserting to kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't limit the Buddha's reasoning for that to just this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, part of that was, I would imagine, asking them permission to kind of, like, compromise their survival chances a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that was a huge ask.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can kind of use that as an excuse today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I have my parents, but, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it that same situation?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most likely not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, they have a different insurance.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: As an American.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, and so, that's, so that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if a person has taken on the Buddhist teaching, which you could summarize as saying that attachment is suffering, and then they choose to accumulate more attachments,
[SPEAKER_04]: Willfully, they haven't actually acquiesced to the Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's not that these people understood the dhamma and then proliferated their worthy engagements.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's that they had... they already had worthy engagements when they understood the dhamma to a point where withdrawing themselves from those engagements would have resulted in misfortune for other people.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's a very different situation.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, another thing as well, is that in ancient India...
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, well, I'm not sure exactly what the percentages were, but certainly love marriages were much more rare than they were today.
[SPEAKER_04]: You would be married because your parents forced you to get married when you were, like, even before you turned 20 sometimes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even as children, sometimes they would find their future wife.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you would basically, like, find yourself in that situation.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like you met this person, you fell in love with them, and you, like, for the sake of pure sensual pleasure, you decided to build a life with them.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's more like... like it was either that, or your parents would disown you, or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you find yourself in that situation, and then, again, that... even though externally it might look the same thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, look, he's living with his wife.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm also living with my wife.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But...
[SPEAKER_03]: The whole relationship between husband and wife,
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's conceivably quite different.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people can ask, like, this might be a harsh question, but, you know, just as a thought experiment, if you are in a relationship with someone,
[SPEAKER_03]: If that relationship becomes celibate, for example, just to go to the heart of the matter, just as a thought, as a thought experiment, is that relationship going to stand?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or is your partner basically gonna pack his or her stuff and say, well, if that's what you're gonna do, I'm no longer interested.
[SPEAKER_03]: If that's the conclusion, then you should realize that that relationship, then whatever you tell yourself, that relationship has sensuality,
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, living a celibate life would not result in that relationship breaking up.
[SPEAKER_04]: There would be other purposes for it, apart from this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Such as, you know, taking care of the children that you had before or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: The obstacles, if you read the suttas, or the accounts of when these people would get the right view,
[SPEAKER_02]: Why they got the right view?
[SPEAKER_04]: There's no mention of a meditation technique that they did beforehand or some... like it wasn't... they met the Buddha for the first time.
[SPEAKER_04]: They hadn't been practicing Buddhism before that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it wasn't that they had to spend three months building up their concentration skills in order to be able to understand what he then told them.
[SPEAKER_04]: What made them understand the dhamma was that
[SPEAKER_04]: First, he taught them about the benefits of virtue, the benefits of giving and making good karma.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, he taught them the drawbacks of sensuality, of even the good results that they would get out of doing these good things.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, when their minds were free from hindrances, mainly from sensuality, and established in that that peace of renunciation,
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, he taught them the Four Noble Truths and then they understood on account of that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the factual thing that you have to recognize is, if I haven't understood the dhamma, having received, like, so much more instruction than those people did back then, it can only be because my mind is still
[SPEAKER_04]: To some degree, I don't know exactly how much, but to some degree, it still sees sensuality as pleasant, to the point where it's not able to understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it's still fundamentally, because you can have all the views, theoretical views about the Four Noble Truths or whatever, but fundamentally, if your mind still values sensuality,
[SPEAKER_04]: Your mind doesn't see craving as the root of suffering, because nobody wants to suffer.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if they still value craving, supposedly having understood that craving is the root of suffering, you see that there's a contradiction, that they didn't actually understand.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's what the...
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why all these precepts and virtue and withdrawal from sensuality are prerequisites.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not because, in and of itself, it is the dhamma, because you can abandon all these things for wrong reasons, like members of other sects would do, even back in the Buddha's day, in monastics and other religions, but it's because
[SPEAKER_04]: That is the obstacle.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like when the Buddha became enlightened and then he was hesitating to teach the dhamma, his reasoning was the entire world is clouded, like their vision is clouded by passion.
[SPEAKER_04]: He didn't say, you know, they don't have sufficient focusing concentration skills.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's their view is clouded by desire.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why he felt apprehensive.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that was in, back in the day, in India.
[SPEAKER_03]: in a country which prides itself on its asceticism.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, how many people were not, like, homeless, wanderers?
[SPEAKER_03]: And, I mean, there might have... there were probably a bunch of them on the side of self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that was their obstacle.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's another difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, now, it's basically all the way on the other... it's very unlikely that somebody will now fall into the, like, ascetic self-mortification the way it was back in the Buddha's day.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, a whole bunch of people, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: Wanderers would actually also need not much instruction from the Buddha in order to get it, because they were already living fairly ascetic lives.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas now, it's the other side of the spectrum.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I would...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm even inclined to say that even if somebody is not interested in understanding the Buddhist teaching for whatever reason, still they would benefit
[SPEAKER_03]: From cutting down the desire for comfort, because you will just be so much more capable of dealing with change, when unfortunate things are going to hit you, and they will, sooner or later.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, again, the technological progress is not the issue.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is individuals seeking comfort, which is rooted in not wanting to feel things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you cannot fundamentally not feel things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a tremendous cover-up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Actually, now that we brought up this...
[SPEAKER_04]: I had one sutta, a section of a sutta, I wanted to read out.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you mentioned the self-mortification thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Here it is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, this was when the Buddha was striving, still not having achieved enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, these are three similes that occurred to him.
[SPEAKER_04]: He said, suppose there was a green sappy log and it was lying in water.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, a man comes along with an upper fire stick, thinking to light a fire and produce heat.
[SPEAKER_04]: What do you think, Aggivessana?
[SPEAKER_04]: By drilling the stick against that green sappy log lying in the water, could they light a fire and produce heat?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's a green sappy log and it's lying in the water.
[SPEAKER_04]: That person will eventually get weary and frustrated.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same way, there are ascetics and brahmins who don't live withdrawn in body and mind from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: They haven't internally given up an allayed desire, affection, infatuation, thirst and burning for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Regardless of whether or not they feel violent, painful, sharp, severe, acute feelings, they are incapable of knowledge and vision of supreme awakening.
[SPEAKER_04]: This was the first simile that occurred to me.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, a second simile occurred to me.
[SPEAKER_04]: Suppose there was a green sappy log and it was lying on dry land, far from the water.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, a man comes along with an upper fire stick, thinking to light a fire and produce heat.
[SPEAKER_04]: What do you think, Aggivessana?
[SPEAKER_04]: By drilling the stick against that green sappy log on dry land, far from water, could they light a fire and produce heat?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's still a green, sappy log, despite the fact that it's lying on dry land, far from water.
[SPEAKER_04]: That person will eventually get weary and frustrated.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same way, there are ascetics and brahmins who do live withdrawn in body and mind from sensuality, but they haven't internally given up and allay desire, affection, infatuation, thirst and burning for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Regardless of whether or not they feel violent, painful, sharp, severe, acute feelings, they are incapable of knowledge and vision of supreme awakening.
[SPEAKER_04]: This was the second simile that occurred to me.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, a third simile occurred to me.
[SPEAKER_04]: Suppose there was a dried-up, withered log, and it was lying on dry land, far from the water.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, the man comes along, trying to light the fire stick.
[SPEAKER_04]: By drilling the stick against that dried-up, withered log on dry land, far from water, could they light a fire and produce heat?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, Master Gautama.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's a dried-up, withered log, and it's drying on dry land.
[SPEAKER_04]: Far from water.
[SPEAKER_04]: So...
[SPEAKER_04]: The first scenario is, unfortunately, what a lot of people would be falling into.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, even by body, they're not withdrawing from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, as we mentioned often, the precepts, like the foundation of precepts, that are the very first stage of the gradual training, on account of which all the other things come, like samādhi and all that,
[SPEAKER_04]: They don't have even that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, obviously, if you're not withdrawn in body, there's no way that internally you will have given up that desire.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the situation is even worse than that.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can become a monk and be withdrawn from sensuality bodily and mentally.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like you're not even mentally wishing for
[SPEAKER_04]: The things that you abandon, you basically live almost fully focused on what you're doing as a monk.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, internally, meaning the value, that fundamental value of sensuality hasn't been given up.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if something... if you were to get exposed to some sensually enticing situation, fundamentally, your mind would still regard that as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: You would still be leaning towards it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Means, internally, you haven't given up that craving for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: And unless you reach that point, the Buddha is saying, you won't be able to give rise to knowledge and vision.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is the point where these people got, when the Buddha was teaching them the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_03]: The householders got.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, in that span of time,
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, obviously, it was the Buddha who was so skilled in teaching the dhamma, specifically according to people's dispositions, that he was able to bring them to a point where, at that time, not only bodily, verbally, mentally, but also on that internal level of their value, they had completely
[SPEAKER_04]: In regard to past, present and future, abandon any interest in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: They truly saw it as dangerous and had no interest in it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, he taught them the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then they understood.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like... because the problem would nowadays be...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yes, people would recognize to some extent, I can't be thinking sensual thoughts and engaging in sensuality and be meditating.
[SPEAKER_04]: But they would try to basically compartmentalize the two, so that, you know, during their meditation, there can be no sensuality, but on the outside, there can be.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the problem with that is, you haven't... like, you are, again, withdrawn in body and mind from sensuality, but internally, you still look forward to these things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, so, in the future, at that moment, you have a plan that
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, it doesn't even need to be explicit.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just, you still value this.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, if you were to receive a phone call for some... at that moment, while you're meditating, a phone call for some super amazing opportunity for sensuality,
[SPEAKER_04]: You would be happy.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it is that fundamental value that needs to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you cannot do that if you, for the future, still value sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what I mean is, sensuality cannot be abandoned temporarily.
[SPEAKER_04]: It has to be in that permanent sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, just in a mundane example, as we mentioned before, like, if you want to give up a drug, you can't give it up temporarily.
[SPEAKER_04]: Nobody who says, I won't drink for two weeks, is actually going to be taken seriously as someone who's trying to give up their alcoholism.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the attitude that needs to be taken.
[SPEAKER_03]: And only then are you actually going to feel the weight of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, when people are considering precepts, the right attitude is, for the rest of my life, I don't want to go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that might initially be scary, precisely because you now need to consider the whole of your life.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't know how long you will live, but right now, you're going to feel the burden.
[SPEAKER_03]: Never am I going to touch this again.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's precisely the whole point.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you don't have that, yeah, then you have basically already missed it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because that's where you feel... that's where you're forced to come face to face with what feelings actually are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Feelings get revealed when you have no way to escape from them.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the boundary that the precepts create.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's a good point.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you're properly cornered, things will become very clear.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have no space to move forward, to move backward, to move left, to move right.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's when you will recognize, no, the problem was never
[SPEAKER_04]: Even this pressure that I felt, the problem was my gratuitous resistance and need to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that will never become revealed for as long as you still do the actions that dissipate that pressure, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because for as long as you allow yourself to do that, you will maintain the view that, oh, it's these things that were the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's these feelings that were the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then,
[SPEAKER_04]: The issue extends as far as, as it says there, you can experience the... Because, think about it, like, why is the Buddha saying ascetics and brahmins who would experience these acute, you know, pains of self-mortification, why do you think he would talk about that in relation to people who are not withdrawn from body and mind, from sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just kind of put the other side of things into perspective.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, but like... but practically, why would someone be seeking this self-mortification?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there's something else they don't want to feel.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the whole self-mortification is in a way also based on not wanting to feel something else.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's in a more sort of broader scope, but... what is it that it...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you're trying to free yourself from suffering, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: But you're not willing to acknowledge the fact that you need to give up sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you're doing self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so that becomes a cover-up that sensuality is part of the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, basically, what I'm trying to say is, it's a way of trying to overcompensate.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like... and you might think, oh, of course, you know, this weird, sort of, random aesthetic practices of sitting on a bed of nails or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Who, what kind of crazy person would be doing that?
[SPEAKER_04]: When you think about it, many of the things that people would do today are on that level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you know, do a ten-day meditation retreat, where I have to sit down,
[SPEAKER_04]: Despite pain in my knees for hours, and like, you know, endure that heightened amount of displeasure, to overcompensate for the fact that in the broader context of your life, you don't want to give up sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's actually... it's not just back in the day, it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No matter
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same like, you know, this New Year kind of resolutions people always like to do, and they last usually one or two months after New Year, because they feel guilty about, you know, how they live life through the whole year, you know, indulging in this or that, so they make this resolution, but yet there is no kind of that deep enough
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like a cycle of over-indulging, over-compensating, over-indulging, over-compensating.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and then the guilt becomes a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is just the mind being restless and remorseful, basically, that you want to cover up.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that whole time that you would be engaging in these self-mortification practices,
[SPEAKER_04]: A.k.a.
[SPEAKER_04]: meditation techniques.
[SPEAKER_04]: The whole thing is, like, on a superficial level, you gave up the interest in sensuality, but you're still with that compulsion of craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: And whatever comes out of it, doesn't matter how good it feels, what kind of release it gives you, it's still going to be underlain by the same
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why it's saying, you actually have to go in that direction of abandoning that more fundamental stuff that you don't want to question.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, none of this you will have to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like as it says, whether or not they feel excruciating pain,
[SPEAKER_04]: On account of self-mortification, they are capable of knowledge and vision, because they actually abandon sensuality bodily, mentally, and even any hopes for the future, any values for it in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this, like, it's really on the level of the questioning, like the point of having a discussion about, kind of, what the lay life is like, as opposed to the monk's life.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not to trick people into ordaining or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's to, like, even if you don't become a monk, like, the people who can be lay and practice dhamma are the people who are, like, actively, like, seriously questioning themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the people in the suttas were not
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you take any of the kings who were noble disciples.
[SPEAKER_01]: They weren't not questioning their lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_04]: They weren't pulling their punches.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you know, the Buddha said lay disciples only have to do this much, so I'll only do this much.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, anything that you justify,
[SPEAKER_04]: That's going to be your obstacle.
[SPEAKER_04]: To stream entry, not to, like, arahantship.
[SPEAKER_04]: Anything that you justify to yourself, knowing that it's craving, is evidence of the fact that you haven't understood that craving is suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you're torturing yourself, factually.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, supposedly, you see that this is suffering, and you still hold on to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You can't do that if there's any real understanding of craving being suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the other thing, related to what you just said, is that if you read all these suttas about... the suttas that people really like to focus on, like, you know, the impermanence and meditation and jhānas and the four satipaṭṭhānas,
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I personally went through it, and it's counted, but...
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, the only times where the Buddha talked about these things to lay disciples, was when they were already sotāpanas.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there's like five cases throughout the entire canon.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was also the one where Sariputta was talking to a brahmin on his deathbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was another disciple as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not in that one, because he was... this is the one where he was saying to practice the Brahmaviharas, and this was the one where the Buddha rebuked Sariputta after the fact, for not giving him, kind of, that next step of teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, but it was clear that he had gotten to the point where he would have become an old disciple.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: This was a Brahmin who was already practicing, kind of,
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why the Buddha always talked about ascetics and brahmins, which is a different category than householders.
[SPEAKER_04]: Those two categories are clearly defined in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what I'm saying is, not necessarily that the robe gives you magical power, but that you will only be able to partake in these things to the extent that you try to live like a monk.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not necessarily... it doesn't mean that you need to give up your children, doesn't mean you need to give up your job, if you already have one.
[SPEAKER_04]: It means, fundamentally,
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you keep your precepts, and you don't accumulate more of these things on purpose, because that clearly shows that you don't have your priorities straight, if the dhamma is what you're looking for.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and another thing we should clarify is the difference between five and eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, Buddha talks about five precepts, but that is just the minimum
[SPEAKER_03]: Ethical standards do not deteriorate as a human being.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is not like, oh, I keep the five precepts, therefore I'm in a position to practice all the things that the Buddha is teaching.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you want to make progress in dhamma, the minimum, the bar has to be eight precepts, or more, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which includes, again, the celibacy, and cutting off the distractions, and things like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And because people might think, oh, householder, plus five precepts, and then I'm going to do retreat and learn the satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because, like I said, the Buddha himself said, what is the obstacle?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's passion, the desire for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, Eight Precepts doesn't automatically free you from passion for sensuality, but you can be sure that if you're engaging in the most sensual acts of all, you're not abandoning passion.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why it's like a prerequisite for abandoning passion, not even that it's going to happen by itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that those... like you said, yeah, so eight precepts are the... you could say eight precepts are the basis for someone who wants to purify their mind from sensual desire, which is the prerequisite for getting the right view, as all the suttas that talk about lay people getting the right view show.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you don't have the Buddha now,
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, you will need to bring yourself to that point where they were, where their minds were dispassionate, through your own effort, through your own relinquishment of things that you know are necessary, and cultivating those values of renunciation, to the point where your mind actually feels more at ease with giving things up on that right level of, you know, your attachments, your possessions, your pleasures.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, with acquiring more.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and that can be said to be the true prerequisite nowadays, if you want to be in the position to come and understand the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, even back then, it was... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what we're saying is, like, back in the day, some people already found themselves in that situation.
[SPEAKER_03]: They listen to a discourse by the Buddha and they get it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nowadays, that's... it's much more unlikely.
[SPEAKER_03]: People can read the the Nikayas ten times and still not get it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: What I hear you say is like people should make an effort as a sort of preliminary step to bring themselves to that level of ethical consideration.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, preliminary practices are not like prostrations and visualizations and repeating a 108-syllable mantra a gazillion times.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is fully on the level of ethics, if by that we mean devaluing sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because there's also Majjhima Nikaya 24, I think, where the Buddha described in the most concise way the sequence of purification.
[SPEAKER_04]: And purification of mind was not the first.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was the second.
[SPEAKER_04]: Purification of virtue, purification of mind comes later.
[SPEAKER_04]: So,
[SPEAKER_04]: People usually take it purification of mind first, then purification of views, and purification of virtue, maybe next life, when I don't... Yeah, more that will follow naturally from those other two steps, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or not even that, because, you know, people might think, okay, like, you know, just...
[SPEAKER_04]: I do what I can in this life, and then in the next one, you know, I'll purify my virtue, because then... Yeah, that's already assuming next life, which is assuming more craving and more suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, so...
[SPEAKER_04]: The primary recognition that you should have is, you have such a wide familiarity with this dhamma, and you still don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even though much less was required for these people to get the right view, that has to be because of this prerequisite not having been met.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can't assume that you are
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, no, you have to assume that if these people were able to understand the dhamma without having kept the eight precepts for ten years, and yet you're hearing more dhamma than them, and you haven't understood, what you will have to bring your mind to that level, and it will happen through this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Through keeping the precepts and cultivating sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, as the Buddha said, not all beings are born equal.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there are different faculties.
[SPEAKER_04]: He said there are some beings who are like...
[SPEAKER_04]: I think he gave a simile of like the lotus plants, which some of them are like right on the surface.
[SPEAKER_04]: Some of them are deep, buried deep down.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, some people, even though they haven't
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, because you haven't found the Buddha's teaching, why would you be keeping the eight precepts?
[SPEAKER_04]: You have no...
[SPEAKER_04]: The natural tendency of the world, everyone around you is doing this, so you will do the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that doesn't mean that your mind is fundamentally equally passionate.
[SPEAKER_04]: Still passionate to some extent, of course, but it doesn't mean that it's equally passionate as everybody else.
[SPEAKER_04]: And only the Buddha or somebody equal to him would be able to know that.
[SPEAKER_04]: To you, it might seem, oh, look, he's also doing the same things as me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so Buddha could see the distinction between somebody just acting circumstantially in certain ways, but their background values were quite different.
[SPEAKER_03]: They were just sort of socialized into a certain situation, but they were not like... it didn't go that deep, the group basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so that means... Then the Buddha comes up with some harsh similes about the drawback of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: It connects with that background value that they might not have been aware of, but because it was there, at one... it at once clicks.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, or not even necessarily having the background value.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you have been hitting it hard for many years with this dhamma that you're practicing and you haven't got the right view, it's because you don't have the starting point that these people have.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then we come back all the way to the beginning.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is a fatal mistake to assume that because you have been born in these materially prosperous times, and with all sorts of technological revolutions and things like that going on, that you are therefore inwardly
[SPEAKER_03]: At the same position, or even in a better position, than those people back in the day were.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's not like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is fully on an on an individual level.
[SPEAKER_03]: And a dhamma that is timeless, cannot be said... that whole narrative of progress, should be given its right place.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's on the level of science, outer, technological progress, not... the inner progress is on the level of virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's an entirely different domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people need to start making that distinction, and then bring themselves within.
[SPEAKER_03]: The current situation, where there are these material benefits, on the level of the virtue, they have to bring themselves to the right point.
[SPEAKER_02]: They could start to question themselves whether they have this inner richness, or maybe poverty.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know.
[SPEAKER_02]: In terms of virtue, these days we can say that we are quite impoverished.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's good conservation, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and it's also
[SPEAKER_04]: The mere fact that you're born in these times already says something about the baseline of your mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, as the Buddha said, humans are deteriorating with time, in terms of their their natural values.
[SPEAKER_04]: So,
[SPEAKER_04]: The fact that you were born... that you are still here, basically, that you're not somewhere else, means that you are kind of riding that same train.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if you were in the more exalted nature, by default, you wouldn't be here right now, most likely.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so being here is not the best place in the universe, let's put it like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, it's good for realizing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So this human world is... Yeah, yeah, but why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because there is that contemplation where the Buddha says that to be born as a human is foremost.
[SPEAKER_03]: But why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, compared to heavenly beings,
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's more comfortable.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's more refined.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's precisely why we are addressing the issue now.
[SPEAKER_03]: But now, it is almost as if, on the human plane, it is going towards the, let's say, deva realm, in terms of the comforts that are available to at least people living in this part of the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is outwardly comfortable, but inwardly an obstacle.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, if people want to get out of the whole realm of existence, they will have to come to terms with that, which is obviously nothing to do with changing anything on the level of society.
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, this is not rebelling against new technological innovations.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it is fully inwardly on the level of the virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, we're not endorsing, what's that called?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's important to emphasize what type of comfort you have to abandon.
[SPEAKER_04]: Fundamentally, it's this emotional dependence on pleasure, like the things that are against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, like I said, a person can choose to not question these fundamental things, where the real gratification and craving is being fed,
[SPEAKER_04]: Like sexual intercourse, entertainment, all these basic things, they don't question that, but they start sleeping on the floor, not using heating, not using a conditioner, and that's not right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or just, you know, like going to the gym and really making physical efforts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, or taking cold showers, or... Yeah, but then at the same time, sitting in a posh restaurant for a big meal, then going to the cinema, and then spending the night with your friends, and stuff like this.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, then in one compartmentalized area, you are actually enduring physical discomfort in the gym, but what you then... just as a mundane example, but then you have to put that in a wider context.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to start giving up those other things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody who keeps eight precepts would not spend two hours in a posh restaurant with wine and candlelight and all the rest of it, then go to the cinema and start partying during the night.
[SPEAKER_03]: But now, that is...
[SPEAKER_03]: Right?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, now we live in times where people sit in an office for 40-50 hours a week, in order to spend one day like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all of that needs to basically go upside down, if you want to now understand what the Buddha was actually teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you abandon that fundamental comfort of gratifying what your senses want,
[SPEAKER_04]: If you actually, well, first and foremost, if you keep that as your value, because most of the issues...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's not that... we're not saying like, you know, ideally you should, but if you can't, well, you have to work from where you are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Take up your precepts today.
[SPEAKER_04]: Take up the eight precepts today.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's understandably going to be difficult, but the problem is that people don't keep that as a value.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, they don't keep in mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, all the jhānas and samādhi and all the refined aspects of the Buddhist teaching starts after this.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, they basically stay complacent with the development of virtue that they have, which is like three and a half precepts sometimes, not even the five.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, like, you stay with that and then you start emphasizing completely other different things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, so, if you actually keep the five precepts and
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if it takes you two years, or ten years, or whatever, but you keep that as your value, that I have to be able to keep a precept in order to practice the dhamma properly.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's a much better position than somebody who just does their best here and there with their precepts, and then tries to go into the completely like, you know, stuff that the Buddha was teaching to monks, like, how do I practice ānāpānasati or something, which he called the abiding of the noble ones, and I want to be able to do it without even, you know, keeping the virtue properly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, just taking the five precepts, like never drinking, absolutely never, intentionally, because even that for people nowadays is a problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: You see Buddhists saying, well, you know, the Buddha also said you're not supposed to be too attached to things, and he said you have to give up the clinging to rites and rituals.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that means you shouldn't hold on to these rules too hard and you need to understand that there's a middle way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas forgetting that the middle way starts with fully keeping the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or we're not living as monks, therefore...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just a fight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, as all of that is already going to be problematic, you might not outwardly be a monk, but inwardly... and the closer you are to keeping those right values, the better your chances are for actually gaining the right understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think, like, one other, like, big difference, like, in our days and in the Buddha's time,
[SPEAKER_00]: With also, like, in our days, now we have so much access to information, like with internet, books, you can read, read, read, like, listen, listen, listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it become very easy to... kind of take the... yeah, kind of take, like, the the gradual training, like, completely upside down, like, contemplating, like, deep stuff and going into the nikāyās and all of that, just in order to basically justify oneself to not make any...
[SPEAKER_00]: In the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the beginning, like from the foundation, what needs to be abandoned from the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think one thing that will be maybe nice to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's kind of connected a little bit, what's the difference between like moderation and the middle way, because you kind of mentioned like this kind of attitude of like
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I can drink a little bit so that I can let go, and then I go back to my kind of meditation technique and stuff like that, but it has nothing to do with the Middle Way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so the Middle Way is basically nothing to do with how much things you take.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, I take half the cake instead of the full amount or something like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Middle Way is in regard to the things that are revealed when you're fully restrained.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, when you never give in to any of these desires, like, that are against the precepts, and you start feeling that pressure to give in to them, the middle way is not denying that pressure, realizing that that is a bodily phenomenon that has arisen on its own, and that, for that very reason, you won't give in to.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not like, it's not mine, therefore I can't give in to it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the opposite, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's not mine, like, as soon as I give in to it, I am taking it as mine.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the middle way, ironically, is revealed by full restraint, not by moderate restraint.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the... but that's also quite important, because, I mean, we don't need to get into that too deeply now, but... because there's the other option, like, you do take
[SPEAKER_04]: on faith, the full renunciation and full restraint, but then you go into seclusion and these things start coming up and now you think it's just about destroying them all and not having anything.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's now the the opposite of self-modification.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the middle way is basically
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why it's like the whole graduate training is forcing you basically to find that middle way.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like give... like I said before, it's giving you no space, so that you have no choice now, but to actually see the escape while those pressures are there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you go into seclusion, if you're not distracting yourself, as we said many times before, with random activities, you will start having thoughts about the things that your mind wants.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there you practice the Middle Way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like we say, like we always say, endure it without acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or the whole talk we did on the origin of attention and enduring things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_04]: You see, the arising of this feeling is not the issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: My craving to act
[SPEAKER_04]: From it or against it, that is the issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is the cause of suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's where the middle way is found.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why, ironically, you need to be fully restrained in order to find the middle way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not start with the middle way in order to determine how much you restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: This would be more like...
[SPEAKER_02]: In your terms, that restraint you're talking about is not on your terms, but in terms of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, because you don't know, even beforehand, how much restraint you need, and you don't even know what craving is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you need to take this on faith, you need to take on the fact that the Buddha said, okay, these actions, if you do them, they will always be rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: You haven't understood craving yet, but you take that on,
[SPEAKER_04]: And, if you if you make a practice out of that, like I said, you don't distract yourself with something else, and you keep in sight that this is what is like... That's why they're called training rules, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: We call them precepts in English, which makes them sound like commandments or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the Pali word is training rule.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, these things are the the foundations for the training of the higher virtue, the higher mind, and the higher wisdom.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, with those training rules, basically, you start to outline where the work is.
[SPEAKER_04]: It creates the table, the working table, where you will be able to practice all the more subtle things that this will just talk about.
[SPEAKER_04]: Going back to the discussion of the of the precepts, another thing that the Buddha did advise lay people as well in the suttas is generosity.
[SPEAKER_04]: That was essentially like the instruction to lay disciples would generally revolve around five precepts and generosity.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's one of the aspects that is quite often put aside, at least in Western forms of Buddhism, because it's like, no, I don't really care about making merit.
[SPEAKER_04]: I want to develop wisdom.
[SPEAKER_04]: I want to become enlightened.
[SPEAKER_04]: But actually, if you were to keep the five precepts, let's say you're not going to keep the eight because it's too difficult yet, for now,
[SPEAKER_04]: If you actually commit yourself to unwavering adherence to the five precepts, and then you try to practice generosity, not on your own terms, but, like, even when it hurts, even when, like, you don't just give, you know, the last penny that remains in your bank account, you actually make a practice out of relinquishing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, when you see that your mind is reacting negatively to this,
[SPEAKER_04]: You actually use that as a practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: That would take you much closer.
[SPEAKER_04]: It wouldn't necessarily be enough for the right view, but it would take you much closer to this dispassion and relinquishment that is necessary to get the right view, than if you just keep even the five precepts and then go on to do a meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why, I mean, the Buddha wasn't teaching at all meditation to laypeople.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if the development has to come from that first, and then, if you manage to upgrade to the eight precepts, then you can start thinking about jhānas and samādhi and all that stuff.
[SPEAKER_04]: And another thing as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there's the five precepts, but I think there's another formulation that they sometimes give in special events.
[SPEAKER_04]: Where you have the five precepts and the three precepts on speech, or four, and then livelihood, something like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's basically a further training in... because, again, like, it's usually sort of that... the problem is, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: You recognize, okay, I can't take on the eight precepts yet, it's too difficult, but then you justify all the other things that lay people will do.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, careless speech, like, talk about sensuality, gossiping,
[SPEAKER_03]: Talks about kings, ministers, politics, wars here and there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And all these things you justify to yourself because you're a layperson.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, actually, if you can at least do that,
[SPEAKER_04]: That would also take you much further in terms of development than anything else you might do by disregarding your virtue and taking these things that don't apply to you.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's, again, the other thing, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: If you really put faith in the Buddhist teaching, and you have understood that... or you have conviction in the fact that craving is suffering, you really need to be looking now, whether in your life, you're actually increasing your acquisitions.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like acquisitions that you didn't have before.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, again, like I mentioned, it's not that these lay people, back in the Buddhist day, they were, you know, totally free to ordain, understood the dhamma, and then they chose to acquire a spouse and children after having understood that freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, like today, you would have people
[SPEAKER_04]: But again, because they put the emphasis somewhere else, rather than this foundation of the training, then they would feel justified, like, I've been practicing for 10 years, I'm very familiar with the dhamma, but, like, I intentionally produced a child.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's at odds with the understanding.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because the thing is, like, you have to recognize.
[SPEAKER_04]: We're not, again, saying... telling people what to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you have to recognize these are two fundamentally opposite directions.
[SPEAKER_04]: To the extent that you can... that you choose one, you cannot choose the other.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, to the extent that you're still actively seeking the other one,
[SPEAKER_04]: That contradicts the supposed statement that you make, that you are really trying to become enlightened.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, again, it can be understood if these things already happened, and then you take on the Buddha's teaching afterward.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, yeah, maybe don't
[SPEAKER_04]: Abandon your five-year-old child if...
[SPEAKER_04]: If it fully depends on you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if, like, you intentionally brought about these attachments and stuff, that goes against the fundamental essence of the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because what did the Buddha say?
[SPEAKER_04]: The Buddha didn't say there are two types of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: In that sutta to Gautami, I think it's in Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gautama Gaut
[SPEAKER_04]: To passion, not to dispassion.
[SPEAKER_04]: To attachment, not to detachment.
[SPEAKER_04]: To accumulation, not to diminution.
[SPEAKER_04]: To delight in company, not to seclusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: To great desires, not fewness of desires.
[SPEAKER_04]: To discontent, not to content.
[SPEAKER_04]: To laziness, not to effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know if I'm missing one.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, self-centeredness, I think, is wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't think that actually comes up.
[SPEAKER_04]: But anyway, so, we were put in the description.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Basically, anything that goes against these things, he says, you should know
[SPEAKER_04]: That is not the teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is not the training.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is not the Buddha's instruction.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he didn't say, you know, the dhamma for lay people can sometimes go hand in hand with passion and with attachment.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's another sutra in the Yantra where the Buddha says, I do not praise the wrong dhamma and the wrong discipline, whether it's for householders or for monastics.
[SPEAKER_03]: I praise the right dhamma and the right discipline, both for householders and monastics, meaning the same dhamma and the same discipline.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's basically just to what extent you take it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not that it's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, eh... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, going back to the generosity and the virtue and the whole gradual teaching that the Buddha would give also frequently to lay people, as we described earlier, all of that is going in a direction of giving up suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, somebody... By giving up acquisition.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, somebody might not go all the way, but people want to become familiar
[SPEAKER_03]: With that direction, where suffering ceases.
[SPEAKER_03]: And we've just been laying, or rather describing, what the foundation of that is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, because you can't do it the other way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just practically doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that, I mean, that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: People try to emphasize the anatta, the anicca, the dukkha, the emptiness, and the magical insights about consciousness first.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, this other stuff is kind of like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Disregard it or... Yeah, or to justify it as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, it's secular time, so we don't need all those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's totally good to do with the assumption.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, because, again, these are called training rules for a reason.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I mean, sure, you can choose to go in that direction, if you want, but at the very least, you can't say that you're practicing the Buddhist teaching.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, people put... slap the name of Buddhism on it, even though
[SPEAKER_04]: They're blatantly contradicting what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure, go and practice your mystical insights or whatever, but don't call it Buddhism if you're not actually following the training that the Buddha outlined.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's really the thing that people should keep in mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not like a moral command of what they should do or what they shouldn't do.
[SPEAKER_04]: But keeping in mind that that is the direction that the dhamma goes in.
[SPEAKER_04]: Complete abandonment of all acquisitions.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, you can choose to take it partially and you will reap the benefits of it only partially.
[SPEAKER_04]: But
[SPEAKER_04]: What would be that partial taking up?
[SPEAKER_04]: It wouldn't be partial taking up of the meditation, which is like the... that requires you to have taking it up at least 90%, let's say.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the very tip of the iceberg.
[SPEAKER_04]: The little bit of it that you could get,
[SPEAKER_04]: would be from this keeping of the five precepts and generosity.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the extent to which you would be able to factually experience some amount of that joy of giving up.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if you see, oh, this...
[SPEAKER_04]: I would only get even more of this.
[SPEAKER_04]: And in a much more refined direction, if I do start keeping the eight precepts, and restrain my senses, and go in the further stages of the gradual training, then you can take it further, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you... whatever you do, you keep in mind that that's the direction that dhamma goes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and you would do it based on having understood that that's the direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and that's...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, you don't cheat yourself.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the real problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: When you cheat yourself into thinking that, basically, you got the same product for 10% of the price.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you go to a store, you see two things, they look identical.
[SPEAKER_04]: One of them cost 10 cents, the other ones cost 200 dollars.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, would anyone in their right mind actually think that they're the same thing?
[SPEAKER_04]: Obviously not.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's what happens.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, the dhamma
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to pay the price, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the dhamma that the Buddha taught comes with that price tag.
[SPEAKER_04]: The other one might look exactly the same, but it's impossible for it to be the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Although, that other one, most of the time, is factually being charged for, whereas the real one is actually offered for free, but the price needs to be paid on another level.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's eh... because it's it's... that's why the Buddha called it like, you know,
[SPEAKER_04]: In the future, the dhamma will be corrupted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but corrupt from within.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not because of some outside invasion, but because a misrepresentation of the dhamma arises.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, from within, the whole thing deteriorates.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, eh... That's really what creates the issue.
[SPEAKER_04]: Back in the day, you had different teachers and stuff, and it was clear, okay, these are the... this is everybody else, and this is the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you were declaring yourself as a follower of the Buddha, it's because, actually, you were a follower of the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_04]: But nowadays, many things, many different things, go under the name of Buddhism, and if, even without making any statement about which one of them is right or wrong,
[SPEAKER_04]: If you look at... look carefully for a few moments, you will see there is internal contradictions that are unresolvable.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, somebody has to be wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, well, yeah, like when you look at a product that comes at a lower price, most of the time it's because it's not actually the same.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not the real deal.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.